Guide to the Shepherd Stevens Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Shepherd Stevens papers
1789-1961
1840-1961
MS 865
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
107
(108 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, architectural drawings, sketches, diaries, photographs, lecture materials, writings, and other documents pertaining to the life of Shepherd Stevens (1880-1962), an American architect and professor of architecture at Cornell (1915-1920) and Yale (1920-1947) universities who was educated at Columbia University (1899-1903) and trained in the Beaux-Arts tradition at the École des Beaux Arts in Paris, France, where he received his diplôme in 1908. The papers also include correspondence, photographs, writings, and other records pertaining to the lives of several of Stevens's family members, including Charlotte Cordelia (Shepherd) Davenport (aunt) and William Bates Davenport (uncle). The collection is a particularly rich and valuable resource for studying architectural education and pedagogy in the early decades of the twentieth century.
Stevens, Shepherd, 1880-1962
Scope and Contents
The papers, spanning 1789-1961 (bulk 1840-1961), consist of correspondence, architectural drawings, sketches, diaries, photographs, lecture materials, writings, and other documents pertaining to the life of Shepherd Stevens (1880-1962), an American architect and professor of architecture at Cornell (1915-1920) and Yale (1920-1947) universities who was educated at Columbia University (1899-1903) and trained in the Beaux-Arts tradition at the École des Beaux Arts in Paris, France, where he received his diplôme in 1908. The papers are a particularly rich and valuable resource for the study of architectural education and pedagogy in the early decades of the twentieth century. Also included in the collection are materials pertaining to the lives of several of Stevens's family members.
Among the twelve records series documenting Stevens's academic, professional, and personal activities, the most significant and extensive include Series II, Correspondence, and Series III, Diaries and Calendars, both of which record Stevens's time as a student, a practicing architect, and a professor of architecture, as well as his travels throughout the world; Series IV, Drawings and Sketches, which comprise student projects, assignments, and sketchbooks undertaken at Columbia and the École, and some professional work Stevens pursued during his brief stint as an architect; Series VI, Lecture and Class Material, which includes student writings, lecture notes,and assignments, as well as teaching materials from Yale; and Series IX, Photographs, which contains images of Stevens, portraits and snapshots of various friends and family members, and a variety of travel photographs, including a series of images taken after World War I in France, where Stevens worked for the American Red Cross documenting wartime destruction. The final series, Series XIII, comprises the papers of several family members who were close to Stevens, including his aunt Charlotte Cordelia (Shepherd) Davenport and uncle William Bates Davenport; these papers consist of correspondence, photographs, writings, and other records documenting a range of personal and professional activities, including events relating to the American Civil War and World War I.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Unknown; probably transferred from the Yale University's Art Library.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in thirteen series: I. Card Indexes, undated. II. Correspondence, 1884-1960. III. Diaries and calendars, 1892-1959. IV. Drawings and sketches, 1890-1957. V. Financial records, 1888-1957. VI. Lecture and class material, 1896-1947. VII. Notes, writings, and speeches, 1888-1956. VIII. Official documents, 1856-1954. IX. Photographs, 1873-1952. X. Postcards, undated. XI. Printed material, 1789-1961. XII. Miscellanea, 1818-1955. XIII. Papers of Stevens's family members, 1822-1931.
Biographical / Historical
Shepherd Stevens was born in Elizabeth, New Jersey on June 29, 1880, the son of Thomas Henry and Mary Ellen (Shepherd) Stevens. His aunt Charlotte (Shepherd) Davenport was appointed his official guardian by the County of Kings, New York on October 8, 1888. Stevens moved to Brooklyn, New York, with his aunt Charlotte (Shepherd) and uncle William Davenport (Yale University graduate of 1867) where he was educated at the Brooklyn Latin School (1896-1899) and Columbia University (1899-1903). While attending Columbia University, Stevens focused his studies on architecture, taking classes that ranged from medieval architectural history and ornament to drawing and design.
Stevens, well-traveled and fluent in French, moved to Paris in the fall of 1904 to prepare for the entrance examinations at the École des Beaux-Arts. He passed the entrance exams in July of 1905 and studied under the French architect, Henri Deglane. He received his diploma in architecture in 1908 and returned to New York the following year. For a short time in 1909 and 1911 Stevens worked as a draftsman for William Wells Bosworth and John R. Pope, respectively. During the latter half of 1911, Stevens joined the architectural firm of Carrère & Hastings where he assisted in executing the designs for the Frick Mansion, which later housed the Frick Collection, located on Fifth Avenue in New York City. In 1913, Stevens designed the architectural plans for the Berlin, New Hampshire, City Hall but ultimately was not the chosen architect.
Stevens accepted a position at Cornell University in 1915 as assistant professor of architecture, where he remained until 1920. While teaching at Cornell, Stevens served in World War I as a lieutenant with the American Red Cross. Stationed in France, he spent three months in Paris with the Department of Civil Service and several months at Château-Thierry working with the Friends Organization in temporary repair work. Before departing for France in June of 1918, Stevens married Mary Wilder Breckenridge on May 23, 1918 and remained married until her death in 1925. Stevens left Cornell in 1920 and moved to New Haven, Connecticut, where he joined Yale University's School of Fine Arts as assistant professor of architecture. He advanced to associate professor in 1924, and was named professor of architecture in 1930, where he remained until his retirement in 1947 when he was named professor emeritus. At Yale he taught classes in architectural history, city planning, and design.
In 1929, Stevens joined four other members of the Yale School of Fine Arts for a series of public lectures on art and architecture and focused his lectures on Egyptian and Assyrian architecture. Stevens earned his BFA in 1922 and an honorary M.A. degree was conferred on him by Yale University in 1926. During the summer of that same year, Stevens studied at the American Academy in Rome. From 1900 to 1952 Stevens traveled extensively both in the United States and abroad. He made over twenty-eight trips to Europe, particularly France and Italy, as well as India, Africa, and Asia for personal enjoyment and to study the architectural monuments and culture. In 1903-1904 he took a trip around the world with his aunt Charlotte and uncle William Davenport.
Throughout his life, Stevens was a member of various clubs and professional societies—the Beaux-Arts Institute of Design, American Institute of Architects, Graduate Club of New Haven, and University Club of New York City—and was religiously affiliated with the Church of Christ at Yale. Stevens married Emily Bradley Quinn on September 2, 1935. Stevens died on February 10, 1962, in New Haven, Connecticut, and is buried at the historic Green-Wood Cemetery in Brooklyn, New York. To honor his aunt and uncle, Stevens donated funds to the Yale School of Architecture and established The William B. and Charlotte Shepherd Davenport Visiting Professorship of Architecture Design. Since 1966 and continuing today the Yale School of Architecture has invited a distinguished architect to join the faculty under the Davenport Professorship.
Charlotte Cordelia (Shepherd) Davenport (aunt) was the daughter of Geo F. (American Civil War Veteran) and Sarah Elizabeth (Boyd) Shepherd. Charlotte became the legal guardian over Shepherd Stevens in October of 1888. On September 9, 1874, she married William Bates Davenport and moved to Brooklyn, New York. Charlotte traveled extensively throughout the United States, Canada, and abroad. She was an avid writer and wrote several books, including her first published in 1918 Thoughts as They Came. She died on December 21, 1931.
William Bates Davenport (uncle), son of Julius and Mary Ann (Bates) Davenport, was born in New York City on March 10, 1847. On his father's side he is an eighth generation descendant of John Davenport, who participated in the founding of New Haven, Connecticut, in 1638. He was educated at the Brooklyn Polytechnic Institute under Professor J. C. Overheiser and graduated from Yale University in 1867. Davenport received an honorary Master of Arts degree from Yale in 1887. Davenport was admitted to the Bar in New York State in 1870 and practiced until 1904, specializing in equity and real estate law.
From 1889 to 1904 Davenport held the office of Public Administrator for Kings County, New York. He was a delegate to the Democratic National Convention of 1884 and was a member of the New York State Constitutional Convention in 1894 (serving as a member of the Committee on Cities and Corporations). His many club and society memberships included the Yale Council, Graduate Club of New Haven, Yale Club of New York, Sons of the Revolution, Society of Colonial Wars, Phelps Association of New Haven, and Wolf's Head, a Yale Senior Society. He died on November 14, 1929.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
General
This collection was processed through the generous support of Trip Levis.
Architects; Architecture -- Study and teaching; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Red Cross; World War, 1914-1918; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Architectural drawings (visual works); Architects; Stevens, Shepherd, 1880-1962; Cornell University -- Faculty; École nationale supérieure des beaux-arts (France); Yale University -- Faculty
- Card indexes, Undated; Series I
  - Catalogue of Shepherd Stevens's Library
    - Architecture-miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Travel (geography) (Box 2)
  - Travel index (Box 2)
    General
    Summaries of travels listing locations, dates of travel, modes of transportation, and companions.
  - DeForest, David Curtis (1774-1825) (Box 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Index of DeForest Family papers
- Correspondence, 1884-1960; Series II
  This series is arranged in chronological order and contains Stevens's incoming and outgoing correspondence with friends, colleagues, and principally family members, including his aunt Charlotte "Lottie" Davenport, his uncle William "Nunkey" Davenport, and his wife Mary Stevens. His correspondence during 1904-1908 provides a vivid picture of his intellectual development as an architect while he studied at the École des Beaux-Arts. Correspondence during the years 1908-1920 includes the largest amount of material on Stevens's relatively brief career as a practicing architect, including letters regarding his work on the City Hall in Berlin, New Hampshire (1913) and the survey and restoration work he did in France during and after World War I (1916 and 1918-1919). During the years 1918-1919, 1922, and 1925 his correspondence to Charlotte and William Davenport and Mary Stevens act as his diary entries. The bulk of the correspondence from 1937 to the mid-1940s largely contains letters to senators and congressional members concerning his political views. During the last twenty years of his life, Yale University corresponded with him regularly, recognizing his donations to the University.
  - 1884-1904 April (Box 4, Folder 1-7)
  - 1904 May-1905 January (Box 5, Folder 1-6)
  - 1905 February-1908 December (Box 6, Folder 1-21)
  - 1909-1913 (Box 7, Folder 1-17)
  - 1914-1918 July (Box 8, Folder 1-17)
  - 1918 August-1919 (Box 9, Folder 1-16)
  - 1921-1926 (Box 10, Folder 1-18)
  - 1927-1960 (Box 11, Folder 1-27)
  - Undated (Box 11, Folder 28-30)
  - Autographs, Undated (Box 11, Folder 31)
- Diaries and calendars, 1892-1959; Series III
  The diaries, arranged in chronological order, provide information about Stevens's day-to-day activities and interactions. He writes in detail about his travels, his visits to an array of architectural monuments, and his interactions with various individuals. Several diaries from 1899 to 1908 contain sketches and architectural details by Stevens. The calendars in this series summarize his daily activities as an architect and a faculty member at Cornell University and Yale University.
  - Diaries
    - Diary Index, 1904-1912 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Memorandum of life events, 1892-1916 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - 1892-1903 February (Box 12, Folder 3-29)
    - 1903 February-1904 May (Box 13, Folder 1-15)
    - 1904 May-1907 March (Box 14, Folder 1-13)
    - 1907 March-1912 May (Box 15, Folder 1-14)
    - 1912 November-1918 June (Box 16, Folder 1-12)
    - 1918 June-1925 September (Box 17, Folder 1-9)
    - 1926 June-1929 September (Box 18, Folder 1-6)
    - 1930 June-1934 August (Box 19, Folder 1-10)
    - 1935-1952 (Box 20, Folder 1-10)
  - Calendars
    - 1908-1927 (Box 21, Folder 1-6)
    - 1929-1942 (Box 22, Folder 1-5)
    - 1943-1954 (Box 23, Folder 1-6)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 24, Folder 1-3)
- Drawings and sketches, 1890-1957; Series IV
  This series includes a variety of design and creative work undertaken by Stevens, as both a student and a practicing architect, as well as by others. The series is divided into two subseries: Individual drawings and sketches; and Sketchbooks.
  - Individual drawings and sketches
    - Book plate and Christmas card drawing, 1919, undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous architectural drawings, Undated (Box 25, Folder 2)
      Includes floor plans, elevation, conceptual sketches, and drawings
    - Miscellaneous pencil drawings, 1890-1899 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Professional work
      Professional work includes some of the architectural projects on which Stevens worked as a practicing architect, excluding the Frick Mansion in New York City, which is not part of this collection.
      - Office building designed by W.C. Frohue and S. Stevens Associates in New York City, 1910 (Box 26, Folder 2)
      - Miscellaneous pencil drawings, 1910-1919 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - City Hall, Berlin, New Hampshire
        - Basement plan and elevation, Circa 1913 (Folder 27)
        - Second floor plans, Circa 1913 (Folder 28)
        - Front and rear elevations, Circa 1913 (Folder 29)
        - First floor and revised floor plans, Circa 1913 (Folder 30)
      - Elevation drawings, floorplans, and sketches, 1917-1919 (Box 31, Folder 1)
      - Château-Thierry--World War I restoration work in France, 1918 (Box 25, Folder 3)
        See also: Corresponding architectural notes in Series VII, Notes, Writings, and Speeches, Box 46, folder 11.
      - Floor plans of residence in New Haven, Connecticut, Undated (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Student work
      Student work includes final drawing projects for classes and studios at Columbia University and the École des Beaux-Arts. Not all of Stevens's student work submitted for credit toward the École diplôme is represented here, but a significant number of drawings exist for studio work undertaken while a student in the primaire classe (primary class) and deuxième classe (second class). This work includes a variety of timed assignments and sketches (esquisse), as well as drawings and detail studies submitted for competitions (concours). The dates provided for most of the École drawings are the dates on which the work was evaluated by a jury of École masters.
      See also: Written guidelines for many of the École drawings, specifically the concours, in Series VI, Lecture and class material, Box 38, folder 1.
      - Columbia University
        - Geometric studies, 1899 October-1900 April (Box 31, Folder 3)
        - Watercolors, figure studies, architectural plans, and landscapes, 1899-1904 (Box 31, Folder 4)
        - Architectural studies of ancient monuments and maps, 1900 June-October (Box 31, Folder 5-6)
        - Figure studies, 1900-1901 (Box 26, Folder 4)
        - Elevations, sections, and details of architectural monuments, 1902 (Box 31, Folder 7)
      - École des Beaux-Arts
        Drawings produced while a student in the primaire classe (primary class) and deuxième classe (second class) at the École des Beaux-Arts include a variety of timed and competition (concours) assignments required for the diplôme and evaluated by a jury of masters--the esquisse d'admission (twelve-hour admission sketch) comprising a building plan, section, and elevation; several longer projets rendus (including a primary school, an archaeological museum, a jail) for the competition known as the concours d'émulation; and a detail drawing submitted for the concours sur éléments analytiques. The subseries probably does not include all of the design work completed by Stevens while he attended the École.
        See also: Written guidelines for many of the concours in Series VI, Lecture and class material.
        - Reproductions of medal-winning drawings, 1905-1908 (Box 26, Folder 5)
        - Un Pavillon d'angle d'une Cour d'honneur, esquisse d'admission, 1905 July 4 (Folder 26A)
        - Une Étude de proportions, concours sur éléments analytiques, 1905 October 31 (Folder 26A)
        - A circular staircase, concours sur éléments analytiques (deuxième classe), 1906 January 3 (Folder 26A)
        - La Geôle d'une Maison d'arrêt, projet rendu, Probably 1906 March 6 (Folder 26A)
        - Une Justice de paix, concours d'émulation, 1906 May 1 (Folder 26A)
        - Exercices d'Histoire de l'Architecture, Probably 1906 May 22 (Folder 26A)
        - Un petit hôtel particulier (elevations and sections), projet rendu, 1906 July 3 (Folder 26B)
        - Un petit hôtel particulier (plans), projet rendu, 1906 July 3 (Folder 26B)
        - Une Sépulture de famille, projet rendu (deuxième classe), 1906 July 31 (Folder 26B)
        - Un petit Musée archéologique, projet rendu(deuxième classe), 1906 November 6 (Folder 26B)
        - Une Ruche, probably concours Labarre, 1907 January 14 (Folder 26B)
        - Un escalier droit (elevation, plan, and section),projet rendu, 1907 March 5 (Folder 26B)
        - Un escalier droit (sections),projet rendu, 1907 March 5 (Folder 26B)
        - Une Ecole primaire, projet rendu concours(deuxième classe), 1907 April 30 (Folder 26B)
        - Une Ecole d'horticulture, Esquisse-Esquisse(deuxième classe), 1907 July 12 (Folder 26B)
        - Gloria Victis monument, 1908 (Folder 26C)
        - Lakeside house design, concours 12-hour sketch, Undated (Folder 26C)
        - Plans for a bath, Undated (Folder 26C)
        - Un garage de voitures automobiles, Undated (Folder 26C)
        - Winter garden design, Undated (Folder 26C)
        - Staircase drawings, Undated (Folder 26D)
        - Unidentified elevations, sections, plans, and renderings, Undated (Folder 26D)
        - Detail drawings and calculations, 1906 and undated (Folder 26E)
          No Subnote Content
      - Miscellaneous architectural drawings
        - Circa 1899-circa 1908 (Box 31, Folder 8)
          Includes sketches of Greek vine patterns, ceiling decorations, and church façade
        - Circa 1904-circa 1908 (Box 31, Folder 9)
          Includes architectural plans and sketches
    - By others
      - Architectural ornament cards, Undated (Box 26, Folder 6)
      - Bierstadt, Albert, 1894 (Box 26, Folder 7)
      - Harrison, Richard Edes, Undated (Box 31, Folder 10)
      - Mahoney, James Owen, 1956-1957 (Folder 36)
      - Robertson, Percy, Undated (Box 26, Folder 8)
      - Van Loon, William Hendrick, Undated (Box 26, Folder 9)
      - Weissbuch, Oscar, 1931 (Box 26, Folder 10)
      - Yale University, School of Architecture, 1928, undated (Box 25, Folder 4)
      - Hand drawn "German map-country north of Gland, found in the cave of a house in France", 1918 (Box 25, Folder 5)
      - Miscellaneous paintings and drawings, 1930-1947, undated (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Sketchbooks
    Sketchbooks contain detail drawings, figure studies, and renderings of landscapes and architectural monuments. Nearly all of these drawings are identified with dates, locations, and brief notes.
    - Student work, Columbia University
      - 1899-1903 (Box 32)
      - 1900-1903 (Box 33)
    - Europe and India
      - 1894 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - 1902 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - 1902 May-June (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - 1902 July (Box 34, Folder 4)
      - 1902 July-October (Box 34, Folder 5)
      - 1903 (Box 34, Folder 6)
      - 1903-1904 (Box 34, Folder 7)
      - 1904 August (Box 34, Folder 8)
      - 1905 May (Box 34, Folder 9)
      - 1906-1912 (Box 34, Folder 10)
      - 1907 (Box 34, Folder 11)
    - Europe, North America, and India
      - 1908 (Box 35, Folder 1)
      - 1908-1910 (Box 35, Folder 2)
      - 1913 (Box 35, Folder 3)
      - 1921 (Box 35, Folder 4)
      - 1922 (Box 35, Folder 5)
      - 1925 (Box 35, Folder 6)
      - 1925-1926 (Box 35, Folder 7)
      - 1926-1927 (Box 35, Folder 8)
      - 1928-1929 (Box 35, Folder 9)
      - 1930 (Box 35, Folder 10)
      - 1932-1933 (Box 35, Folder 11)
      - 1937-1947 (Box 35, Folder 12)
      - 1948 (Box 35, Folder 13)
- Financial records, 1888-1957; Series V
  - Bank records
    - Account books
      - 1901-1903 (Box 37, Folder 1)
      - 1909-1913 (Box 37, Folder 2)
      - 1912-1915 (Box 37, Folder 3)
      - 1917 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - Account statements and checks, 1903, 1917, 1920 (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Estate inventory, 1907-1914 (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Personal expense record books
    These records detail both study and travel expenses.
    - 1888-1900 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - 1908, undated (Box 37, Folder 8)
    - 1905-1911, undated (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - 1920-1949, undated (Box 37, Folder 10)
  - Receipts
    - Charitable donations and dues, 1913-1957 (Box 37, Folder 11)
    - Medical, 1914-1915 (Box 37, Folder 12)
    - Purchases and bill payments
      - 1903-1913 (Box 37, Folder 13)
      - 1914-1915 (Box 37, Folder 14)
      - 1920-1922, 1925-1926, 1938 (Box 37, Folder 15)
    - Rent, 1913-1916 (Box 37, Folder 16)
    - Restaurants and hotels, 1908-1921 (Box 37, Folder 17)
    - Stocks, bonds, and earned wages, 1908-1921 (Box 37, Folder 18)
    - World War I restoration work in France, 1918 (Box 37, Folder 19)
- Lecture and class material, 1896-1947; Series VI
  - Student work
    - Assignments and graded work
      - Architectural essays, 1900-1902 (Box 39, Folder 1)
      - Composition essays, 1897-1899 (Box 39, Folder 2-3)
      - Competition (concours) guidelines, École des Beaux-Arts, 1904-1906 (Box 38, Folder 1)
        See also: Series IV, Drawings and sketches, Boxes 26A and 26B, for several of the drawings Stevens submitted for École competitions (p. 11-12).
      - Course grade reports, 1896-1901 (Box 39, Folder 4)
      - Entrance examinations, 1898-1899, 1902 (Box 39, Folder 5)
      - Geometry book, École des Beaux-Arts, 1906 March (Box 38, Folder 2)
      - Graduation project, country home description, École des Beaux-Arts, 1908 November 16 (Box 38, Folder 3)
      - By others, 1905-1906 (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - Lecture notebooks
      - American Academy in Rome, 1926 (Box 39, Folder 7)
      - Brooklyn Latin School, Undated (Box 39, Folder 8)
      - Columbia University
        - 1900-1901 (Box 39, Folder 9)
        - 1900 October-1901 May (Box 39, Folder 10)
        - 1900-1903 (Box 39, Folder 11)
        - 1901 October-1902 April (Box 39, Folder 12)